Guide to the Edward J. Shourek Photographic Collection, 1913-1920 AIS.1991.19b
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Edward J. Shourek Photograph Collection
1913-1920
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Shourek, Edward J.
AIS.1991.19b
196 items (8) boxes
This collection consists of the photographic glass-plate negatives of Edward J. Shourek for the years 1913-1920. There are 196 negatives that document Shourek's activities in the Lincoln-Lemington area of Pittsburgh's East Liberty neighborhood from 1913-1920. Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
Biography
Edward J. Shourek was born in Pittsburgh in June 1895. The Shourek family lived at 811 East View Avenue in the Lincoln-Lemington area of Pittsburgh's East Liberty neighborhood. As a young man, Shourek's hobby of photography captured family life in Pittsburgh during the early 1900s. Subjects of his photographs were the East Libery neighborhood, Central High School, George Westinghouse High School, family vacations, other families and friends. Shourek graduated from Pittsburgh's Central High School in 1914 and soon after enlisted in the United States Army Corps of Engineers where he worked as a draftsman. Shourek worked as a draftsman in the Army until 1965. Shourek was married to Florence Love and had one daughter, Marion Shourek Slabaugh of Portland, Oregon. Edward J. Shourek died in Pittsburgh on February 8, 1966.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the glass-plate negatives of the Edward J. Shourek Photograph Collection, 1913-1920. The collection consists of 25 series which are subject oriented. The negatives are ordered chronologically within each series, except for series that have no dates. Each negative is described according to the subjects in the image, ie. person, or place. In addition to subject description, many negatives include a phrase created by Shourek that depicts the scene, these are indicated by quotation marks. Pittsburgh sites include Central High School, Westinghouse High School, Fern Hollow, Syria Mosque, and Reimer and Brothers, Inc. Sites from family vacations include Akron, Ohio; Buffalo, New York; Niagara Falls, New York; and Huntington County, West Virgina. People identified in the photographs include Ella Shourek (Gerding), Martha Shourek (Stuck), Ida Shourek (Sant), Julia Shourek, Theodore Shourek, Uncle Luke, Aunt Tillie, Mary Ewart, Kate Flavin, Erma Gill, Billy Goodyear, Bob Holden, Catherine Kohne, Helen Lundquist, Elaine Lundquist, Alfred Mound, Karyn Mound, Joe Parrish, Jimmie Rule, Edward Stack, and Margaret Wightman. The photographs also include images of dogs, cats, horses, squirrels, groundhogs, and farm scenes.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were acquired from Mr. John Rischnavsky, 1991
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/edward-j-shourek-photographs.
Previous Citation
Edward J. Shourek Photograph Collection, AIS.1991.19b, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Edward J. Shourek, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, ais 91:19b, Photographs, 1913-1920, Archives of Industrial Society, Hillman Library, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social life and customs -- Photographs; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Photographs; Shourek family -- Photographs; Central High School (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Photographs; Shourek, Edward J.; Westinghouse High School (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Photographs
- Home, 1911-1918; I.
  - Buster (dog), Spring, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Edward Stack standing outside with dog, 1912
  - One of Reel's Dogs, Spring, 1912
  - Ma, Emily and Ida posing outside, 1913
  - Emily and Ed posing out in the garden, 1913
  - Ida, Martha and Emily with dogs and cats in garden, 1913
  - Group of four women and two men posing in backyard, 1913
  - Bernice, Ed and Martha in garden, 1913
  - Emily in garden
  - One of Reel's dogs, 1913
  - Ernst in backyard, Autumn, 1913
  - Central High School 1914 flag
  - Ham, Helen and Martha in backyard, 1914
  - Billy (pup) on step, 1915
  - A pup, 1915
  - A pup, 1915
  - Pup on front step, 1915
  - Peony bush, June, 1915
  - Bush Stack's squirrel in cage, November, 1915
  - Page from the Pageant, Edward in Page's costume with American flag, 1916
  - Reggie (dog) among potted plants
  - Buster and Dodo (dogs) on front porch, 1916
  - Ted in dress suit, first formal, March, 1916
  - The wild patch, garden in backyard, May 18, 1916
  - Fireworks, Garaboldi celebration, "A Rocket", July 17, 1916
  - Fireworks, Garaboldi celebration, "The Bombs Bursting in Air", July 17, 1916 (Box 2)
  - Fireworks, Garaboldi celebration, "Golden Rain", July 17, 1916
  - Edward's study stable on his side of the room, September 19, 1916
  - Bob Holden, Supreme Secretary, December 31, 1916
  - Last heavy snow, view from Edward's front window, March, 1917
  - Last heavy snow, view from Ida's room, March, 1917
  - Martha in new spring suit, 1918
  - Snow storm, back lot, April 12, 1918
  - Backyard from shop, June, 1918
  - Jess (cat) sitting on window sill, June, 1918
  - Pa and Uncle Joe in backyard, July 4, 1918
  - Uncle Joe on back porch, July 4, 1918
  - Alfred and Karyn in backyard, undated
  - Martha by fence in backyard, undated
  - One of Reel's dogs on steps, undated
  - Reel's dog on steps, undated
  - Ida standing by fence in backyard, undated
  - Sport (dog) sitting by fence, undated
  - Two puppies, undated
  - Dog sitting on couch, undated
  - Ida on sidewalk by yard, undated
- Farm, 1913-1920; II.
  - The clover field, 1913
  - Young corn field before storm, 1913
  - Lennon's dog Shep, 1913
  - Cherry, Daisy, Blanche, Star, Durno (cows), and Dick (dog) in the pasture, 1913
  - Julie, Helen, Emily, and Grace (girls) with Shep and Tige (dogs) on lawn, 1913 (Box 3)
  - Dude on Phoebe (woman riding horse), 1913
  - Bonny (cow), 1913
  - Lennon riding mower pulled by two horses, 1913
  - Scene in pasture, 1913
  - Helen standing in field, July 1913
  - Girls on road, July 1913
  - Potato field, 1914
  - "Stuck on the big hill," car on dirt road, 1914
  - The road looking west, 1914
  - Maiden Blush Apple Tree, 1914
  - Groundhog, 1914
  - Hank, Dude and Ebberjay sitting on a tree stump, 1914
  - Hank, Ebberjay and Emily sitting on a tree stump, 1914
  - Group of boys and girls on bank of creek, 1914
  - A fern in Uncle Joe's woods, 1914
  - Hank, Ebberjay and Shep (dog) on a fallen tree, 1914
  - Woodchuck, 1914
  - Dude and Ebberjay on a tree over creek, 1914
  - Dogs digging woodchucks, 1914
  - Dogs digging woodchucks, 1914
  - Hank, Dude and Ebberjay on tree stump, 1914
  - Scene in Uncle Joe's woods, 1914
  - Apple tree, 1914
  - Dickie (little boy) standing outside, 1920
- Central High School, 1913-1914; III.
  - Trophy case, 1913 (Box 4)
  - Class 11-12 group photo, June 1913
  - Toots, Ashford, and O'Connel on school steps, 1914
  - Gus at Doctor Dewey's desk the day of the fire, 1914
  - Jimmie Rule at desk, 1914
  - Catherine "Kitty," Roach, Midge, and Pest sitting on school steps, 1914
  - Midge outside of school, 1914
  - Midge, Boob, and Shrimp on roof, 1914
  - Stage setting for "Einer Muss Heiraten", 1914
  - Stage setting for "Einer Muss Heiraten", 1914
  - Critical study class, "Teacher, Teacher", 1914
  - Critical Study Class, 1914
  - Pest and Shrimp on roof, 1914
  - Shep on steps of school, 1914
  - Boob and Midge on roof ventilator, 1914
  - The flag raising, Roach and Boob on roof, 1914
  - "Beauty and dignity personified. Its great to be a wonderful detective." Catherine Kohne and Mary Enart on front steps with Joe Parish peeping from behind a pillar, 1914
  - Inside of Edward's desk, 12-5, Spring, 1914
- Akron, Ohio, 1913-1914; IV.
  - Annie's place, group in front yard, 1913
  - Annie's place, group in front yard, 1913
  - Fritz (little boy) standing on chair, 1914
- Lennon's Horse, 1913; V.
  - Horse harnassed to buggy, 1913 (Box 5)
- The Lundquist Family, 1914; VI.
  - Elaine (baby girl) sitting on stool in yard, 1914
  - Helen (young girl) on rocker in yard, 1914
  - Helen (standing) and Elaine (on stool) in yard, 1914
  - Helen and Elaine on stool in yard, 1914
  - The Lundquist family, 1914
  - The Lundquist family, 1914
- The Reimer Family Picnic, 1914; VII.
  - "I love to be among the girls." Vetter, McCarthy, Raider, Flavin, Gildea, Frank, Schindler, Fahnestock, Magurie, Becker, 1914
  - "I love the ladies." Fahler's farm, 1914
  - Becker, Fahnestock, Vetter, Burrows, Maguire, Shourek on fence rail, 1914
  - Maguire at the spring, 1914
- Shopgang, 1914; VIII.
  - Kiljoy, flashlight, boy doing lathework, 1914
  - Midge, flashlight, boy doing work on motor, 1914
- Clark's Camp, 1914; IX.
  - "Writing that wonderful name in the sand," group of seven, 1914
  - "On the island," group of twelve people with two canoes, 1914
- Buffalo, New York, 1914; X.
  - McKinley Monument, 1914
- Big Willow Tree Camp, 1915-1917; XI.
  - Big Willow Tree Camp, path through woods, July 1915
  - "Sailing on the Rushton Branch," two people in sailboat, July 1915
  - Pine tree on Terrace Mountain, July 1915
  - Sport (dog) swimming, "He always flips his tail when he grabs the stick", July 1915
  - Man holding fish on dock, "Roach and his catch", July 1915
  - Allegrippas from the barn, July 1915
  - Man with fishing pole and fish, "Fish, the Fisherman, a Fish Story", July 1915
  - Sport (dog) bringing a stick ashore, Rushton River, July 1915
  - Canoes on river, 1917
  - Scene in Allegrippas, July 28, 1917
  - "Shrimp in the Ruston River," boy in canoe, July 28, 1917
  - "Woolyo Brown on the dock," man standing on dock, July 28, 1917
  - Roach and Woolyo in the "swim", July 29, 1917 (Box 6)
  - "The Spring," shows water bucket, July 29, 1917
  - John and Ed fishing at the base of Allegrippas Ridge, July 29, 1917
  - The Gang: P.M.D., Roach, Shrimp, Spuds, Woolyo, July 29, 1917
  - Shepard Brownie on the cozy rock at the foot of the Allegrippas, July 29, 1917
- Inca, 1915-1918; XII.
  - "Inca Ed and Bess," man and woman standing under flag on steps in front of house, Spring 1915
  - The Avenue, field stretching between rows of trees, Summer 1915
  - Tomato plants in Inca garden, Summer 1915
  - Cucumber plants, 9 inches long, 3 inches diameter, Summer 1915
  - Mess tent, group eating during the day, 1917
  - "My tent", August 12, 1917
  - Belle Wightman in front of "my tent", August 25 1917
  - Cornelia in lazyback chair, June 9, 1918
  - "Count and Cornmeal," man and woman standing by tree, June 9, 1918
  - Erma Gill, June 9, 1918
  - Erma on grip, July 7, 1918
  - Erma in hammock reading, September 8, 1918
  - Erma in lazyback chair, September 14, 1918
  - Erma on path, holding grip, September 14, 1918
  - Ed and Erma on porch swing, September 14, 1918
  - Erma after falling out of the hammock, September 15, 1918
- Huntingdon County, 1915; XIII.
  - Picture of BWTC from Allegrippas Ridge, July 1915 (Box 7)
  - The road up Terrace Mountain, EJS dressed in pages costume and holding banner, July 1915
- George Westinghouse High School, 1916; XIV.
  - The sewing class, girls, May 18, 1916
  - The cooking class, six girls, May 18, 1916
  - The cooking class, May 18, 1916
- Pittsburgh, 1916; XV.
  - "The Thirsty Clansman," JHB in a cloak holding a walking stick at a brook, 1916
  - Tree on Boulevard, undated
- Uncle Luke's, 1918; XVI.
  - Uncle Luke standing on steps outside house, 1918
  - Aunt Tillie on back steps, 1918
  - Ernst on back steps, 1918
  - Bernice on back steps, 1918
  - Uncle Luke on back steps, 1918
  - Bernice standing on back steps, 1918
- Niagara Falls, 1920; XVII.
  - Rapids above falls, September 12, 1920
- McCartney's, no date; XVIII.
  - Front of house with person on front steps, undated
  - Bunch on porch, four women and two men, undated
  - Bunch in backyard, four children, two women, and a man, undated
  - View of back of house, woman and two children, undated
- Reymer and Brothers, Inc., no date; XIX.
  - Store from balcony, interior of store, located on 6022 Penn Avenue, undated
- Scene, no date; XX.
  - Wooded creek scene, undated
- Animals, no date; XXI.
  - French poodle, undated
- Reymer's, no date; XXII.
  - Fisher standing outside of building, undated
  - Coward Flannelsocks and Kate Flaven, man and woman, undated
- Fern Hollow, no date; XXIII.
  - Field with trees in background, undated
  - Clump of trees, undated
- Unlabeled, no date; XXIV
  Scope and Contents note
  Series XXIV. contains unlabeled negatives identified by subjects on the image.
  - Dog "dressed up" in house, undated (Box 8)
  - Woman in field, undated
  - Syria Mosque, undated
  - Group picture in woods, 20 people, undated
  - Allegrippas Ridge and lake or river, undated
  - Boy beside creek, undated
  - Man wearing Shriner hat, undated
- Copies, 1914-1918; XXV
  Series XXV. contains copies of negatives or photographs of other photographs. Series in chronological order.
  - P.M.D.'s negatives drying on the wall, 1914
  - E.J.S.'s negatives drying on the wall, 1914
  - Margareth Wightman's portraits on the wall, 1916
  - Margaret Wightman's negatives drying, 1916
  - Kindergarten class, 1918
  - Billy Goodyear standing in side yard, 1918
  - Billy Goodyear negative drying on wall, 1918
  - Billy Goodyear negative drying on wall, Spring 1918
  - Martha's pictures on the drying rack, June 1918
  - Frank, Joe Robing posing in good clothes, June 1918
  - Blythe B, age 13, seated next to table, June 1918
  - Lettie "sunshine" Burnette, posing seated next to table, June 1918
  - Ex Libris - H. Zief, group's symbol, June 1918
  - Ex Libris - H. Zief, June 1918
  - Ida and Danny, June 20, 1918
  - E.M.G. from senior number of "The Peabody" taken from the yearbook, copy shows Erma, Mildred, Gill, and Samual B. Goodstone on page 18 of "The Peabody", September 18, 1918
  - The Shakers, taken for J.H.B., undated
- Oversize, XVI.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This material was added to the finding aid in December 2010.
  - Picture of the boat, "Henry L. Hillman", undated (Map-case 7, Drawer 5)